- 珍？- 陛下
- Jane? - Your Majesty.
我们聚集在此
We are come here together.
在上帝面前 诸位一起
before god and these witnesses.
见证亨利八世
to join in Holy matrimony Henry VIII,
英格兰和法兰西国王
King of England and France,
信仰的守卫者
defender of the faith,
英格兰教会最高领袖
Supreme Head of the Church of England,
和珍·西摩女士的神圣婚姻
and the Lady Jane Seymour.
若诸位之中
And if there be any among you…
有谁对他们的婚姻
who may imagine some impediments…
存有异议
as to why they should not be married,
请现在提出
Let them now speak out,
否则永缄其口
or forever hold their tongue.
谢谢你给我的礼物 太漂亮了
Thank you for my gift, it's so very beautiful.
须臾该当谢谢你给我的「礼物」才对
I soon trust to thank you for mine.
去跳舞好吗
Shall we join in the dance?
音乐
Music.
- 我很内疚 - 为什么
- I feel guilty. - Why?
因为有时我竟会忘了你有多美
Because sometimes I forget about how beautiful you are.
我想她会使他快乐的
I think she'll make him happy.
老天帮忙 我们都可以安心了
God's help, we'll all be happy now.
我好像不认识你 女士
I don't recognize you, my lady?
你是新进宫的吗
Are you new at court?
是的 我将成为王后陛下的女侍官之一
Yes, Sir. I am to be a maid to her Majesty.
请问芳名
What's your name?
厄苏拉·米塞尔登女士
Lady Ursula Misseldon.
知道我是谁吗
You know who I am?
您是弗兰西斯·布赖恩爵士 久闻大名
You're Sir Francis Bryan. I've heard about you.
都听说了些什么
What have you heard?
你喜欢脚踏两只船
You like to board other man's boats.
我相信不久后
I trust that I shall be seeing.
我们会常见 米塞尔登女士
a lot more of you, Lady Misseldon.
既然国王的两位女儿
Since both the King's daughters.
都因没有合法地位而失去了继承权
have been declared illegimate and unfit to rule,
我们只能期望王后尽快怀上孩子
we must trust the queen to conceive a child quickly.
我仍然担心 安妮的死
I still fear, with Anne's death,
使我们失去了忠实的朋友和坚强的后盾
we've lost a great friend and a powerful supporter.
如果新王后真如谣言所说
If the new Queen favors the Catholic religion,
是个天主教徒
as she is rumored to do,
那我们的整个改革就可能陷于危险境地
then our whole reformation is surely in jeopardy.
很吃惊
What a suprise,
你竟然非常不信任国王陛下
you have such little faith in the king.
除非我们加紧解散那些妓院
Unless we press ahead the dissalution of those brothels.
灭除那些所谓有良知的下流胚们
and slaughter whores of the conscience.
那些修道院啊
The monasteries.
奉圣父 圣子 及圣神之名 阿门
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti. Amen.
全能的永生的真神 求主加增我们的信心
Almighty and Everlasting God give onto us the increase of faith.
如同您许诺的赐我们希望与慈悲
hope and charity and that we may obtain that which Thou dost promise,
按照您的旨意使我们相爱
make us to love that which Thou dost command.
靠耶酥基督 我们的主
through Jesus Christ, our lord.
阿门
Amen.
夫人 如果可以
Madam, If I may,
我有份结婚礼呈送陛下
I have a wedding gift for Your Majesty.
它原先归凯瑟琳王后所有
It once belonged to Queen Katherine.
谢谢
Thank You.
国王陛下驾到
His Majesty, the King.
- 吾妻 - 夫君
- Wife. - Husband.
我想我们不必当众进行
I don't think we need to proceed in public.
至少不是这次
not this time.
陛下
Majesty.
（约克郡 英格兰北部）
（索里修道院）
让路 国王特使驾到
Make way, the King's commissioners.
确保万事周全
Be assure everything is accounted for.
遵命 法兰克士大人
Yes, Dr. Frankish.
法兰克士大人 这儿有个富婆
Dr. Frankish, here's a wealthy Madonna.
这件不错
Here is a fine one.
丝质外套 大量珠宝 价值连城
Coat of silk, ton of jewels, wealth property.
好了 女士
Well, Lady,
现在是不是一无所有了
are you stripped now?
阿斯克先生
Mr. Aske.
看他们都做了什么 约翰 看看吧
Look what they've done, John. Just look.
全是克伦威尔搞的
It's all Cromwell's doing.
克伦威尔和伦敦的那帮异教徒
Cromwell and that sect of heretics in London,
那个混蛋
that bustard.
我一定要告诉你 阿斯克先生
I'll tell you this Mr.Aske, people,
大家再也不想袖手旁观了
They're no longer willing to stand by,
不想眼看着自己的信仰
and watch their faith,
自己所关心的一切
and everything that they care for,
都被剥夺
being stripped away.
我听说昨天
I heard just yesterday,
克伦威尔的两个特使
that two of Cromwell's commisioners were attacked.
在林肯郡被袭
in Lincolnshire.
而在这里 约克郡
And here in Yorkshire,
群众之中有人
and a man of the commons.
在自己的教堂里挺身而出
stood up in his own church.
呼吁我们去追随耶稣
and said go away to follow the crosses.
因为等他们将一切夺走之后
For what they've taken from us,
我们就会无所追随
we can follow them no more.
你想让我怎么做呢 约翰
What am I supposed to do, John?
林肯郡以及其他地方的民众
The commons here, in Lincolnshire, everywhere.
都已准备战斗
They're prepared to fight,
去拯救他们的所爱
to save what they love.
但他们需要首领
But they need captains,
他们需要有智慧 有学识的人来领导他们
they need clever, educated man to lead them.
我绝不是个领袖人物 约翰
I'm no leader, John.
别仓促决定
Don't decide now.
我们将会召开一次会议
We'll call a meeting,
会后决定
then decide.
为了上帝的爱
For the love of God.
来看看这个
Take a look at that.
我们的特使在索里修道院发现的
Our commisioners found it in Sawly Abbey.
这是怎么弄的？
How was it done?
自己看
See it yourself.
人们以为圣徒的骨骼依然是活的
People thought the saint's bones were alive…
他们被用来做祈福
use it work for benedictions.
如果他们向教堂及罗马捐一点钱的话
If they pay a little money they had to the church and to Rome.
我们的改革进展如何？
How do our reforms progress?
如您所知 大人
As you know, my lord.
议会正在为镇压
Parliament has now voted for the suppression.
小修道院的事情投票
of all the small monastery houses.
而国王特使们的几乎在英格兰每个郡
and the commisioners are upon and about their businesses.
都采取了行动
in nearly every county in England…
有没有受到反抗？
Much opposition?
没有我们预计的多
not as much as we might have expected.
何足担忧？
why should we have expected it?
人们认为
People conceive for themselves.
这些修道院都应该受到谴责
that all these houses should be condemned.
他们的罪过太显而易见了 声色犬马的生活
for their manifest sin: carnal and abundable living.
有人告诉我其中一件趣事
I was told, one anecdote among many.
当我们的特使来到伦敦十字修道僧院时
When our commisioners entered the London houses of the Crossed Friars.
他们竟然看见祈祷者自己乱作一团
They found the prayer himself, in babel disorder.
都全身赤裸 满脸惊愕
both stunned and naked.
他经常以贿赂来逃脱
they often bribes to go away.
确实如此 那些普通人一旦得势
It is true that ordinary people are so greedy.
就会变的过份贪婪
upon these houses when they are suppressed.
他们不分昼夜地搜刮 直到什么都不剩下
they scavenge in the night and day untill nothing is left.
他们甚至拿书本去当厕纸
they even take the books, to use for paper in their houses of easement.
国王陛下的财政收入如何了？
How about the gains of King's treasure?
到目前为止 我估计
So far, by my reckoning,
我们已经让国王的收入翻倍了
we have already doubled the King's income.
接收的修道院的土地
and taken in possesion of the monastic lands.
价值数百万英镑
worth many millions of pounds.
数百万？
Millions?
正是 秘书大人
Yes, Mr. Secretary.
爱德华·西摩爵士
Sir Edward Seymour.
爱德华爵士
Sir Edward,
作为国王陛下爱妻珍的兄长
as the brother of His Majesty's beloved wife, Jane,
今天 国王陛下欣然敕封你
It is his Majesty's pleasure today to creat you.
为萨默塞特郡 哈彻之伯查子爵
Viscount Beauchamp of Hache in Somerset,
同时任命你为泽西的总督
also to appoint you a governor of Jersy.
以及北威尔士的大法官
and Chancellor of North Wales.
国王陛下 我深感荣幸
Your Majesty, I'm deeply honoured.
我向您保证 我将为陛下利益
And I assure your Majesty that I would labor…
鞠躬尽瘁 死而后已
unremittingly in your Majesty's interest,
以回报您对我的信任
in the hope of repaying the great trust you've shown in me.
大人 此乃册封您的英王制诰
My lord, here are your Letters patent.
恭喜您的升迁
May I congratulate you on your elevation.
谢谢秘书大人
Mr. Secratary.
托马斯 有何内务？
Thomas, what are the businesses there?
吾王陛下已收到来自皇帝的贺信
Your Majesty has received a letter from the Emperor,
恭喜陛下的新婚
congratulating your new marriage.
他已经不再阻碍
Since he's no further impediment,
并非常急切地寻求结盟
he's very anxious to become a new accommodation.
不错 还有呢？
Good. What else?
玛丽女士也给你来信 陛下
The Lady Mary has also written to you, Majesty.
她想怎么样？
What does she want?
她说 是时候忘记不愉快的过去了
She writes, that it is time now to forget the unhappy past,
她乞求陛下的原谅
she begs to be taken by your Majesty's forgiveness.
并恳求陛下理解
and humbly beseeches you to remember.
「我是个谦卑的女人 也是您的孩子」
that I am a humbled woman and your child.
我绝不会召她回来
I'll never take her back.
除非她先在
Not until she first submit herself to me.
她母亲的婚姻事情上服从王意且付诸书面
the subject of his mother's marriage and surprint.
你可派人前去
You'll send the delegation.
若她真想忘记过去的不幸
if she trully wants to forget the unhappy past,
那就签署文件
then she can stop by signing it.
遵命陛下
Majesty.
马夫
Groom.
弗兰西斯爵士 我有好消息告知
Ah, Sir Francis. I have some good news for you.
国王陛下已经恩准
His majesty has agreed to your appointment.
任命您为枢密官
as a gentleman of the Privy Chamber.
我想我知道了 谢谢
I'm sure I know. thanks for that.
很快我就会给您份差事
I may have a small job for you, soon.
- 大使阁下 - 国王陛下
- Excellency. - Your Majesty.
跟我来 我带你去见一个人
Come with me. there's someone I wish to present you to.
珍王后 请允许我向您引见尤斯塔斯·乔普斯
Queen Jane.Allow me to introduce his Excellency Eustace Chapuys,
皇帝查尔斯五世之大使阁下
Ambassador to the emperor Charles V, Spain.
大使阁下
Excellency.
你们单独谈谈
I leave you to talk in private.
王后陛下 请允许我祝您婚姻幸福
Your Majesty, may I congratulate on your marriage.
也祝愿你身体健康 事事如意
Wish you good health and prosperity.
虽然提议您登王位的那位女士
Although the device of the lady who proceeded you.
最感高兴
on the throne was the most happy.
但我毫无疑问 你自已乃是天命所归
I have no doubt that it is you, yourself who will realise that mortal.
谢谢 阁下
Thank you, Excellency.
我知道皇帝陛下将为有
I know that the emperor will rejoice of.
如此高贵而和善的王后感到高兴
such a virtual ascent and amiable queen on the throne.
毫不夸张地说 我所见到的每个英国人
I must tell you it would be impossible for me to overstate the joy.
在听说你结婚时
and happiness which each Englsih men I have met.
都异常高兴
have expressed to me on hearing of your marriage.
特别是听说您将作为和平使者
Especially, as it is said, that you're a peace-maker who'll be continually.
力促国王陛下与其女玛丽和解
trying to persuade his majesty to restore his daughter Mary to favor.
阁下 我答应你
I promise you, excellency.
我会继续关照玛丽女士
that I would continue to show favor to the Lady Mary.
我将尽最大的努力
And do my best to deserve the title of peace-maker.
也不枉您赠我「和平使者」的称号
you so gallantly have given me.
如果你这么做 我想你会发现的
If you do so, I think you'll find Madam that.
夫人 不用辛劳 也不用生育
without the pain of labour, and childbirth,
你就可以得到拥有女儿的快乐
you'll gain a treasure of the daughter.
一个会比你和国王的亲生孩子
who may please you even more.
更让你开心的女儿
than your own children by the King.
我只能重申 大使阁下
I can only say again, Excellency.
我将尽最大的努力
That I will do my best to restore the peace.
来促使国王和他长女的和解
between the King and his eldest daughter.
- 大使 - 夫人告退
- Ambassordor - Madam.
夫人告退
Madam.
您是她接见的第一位大使
You're the first ambassordor she's received.
她还不习惯这样的会见
She is not yet used to see such audiences.
但有一点他们没错
but it is true what they say.
她善良而平易近人
She is kind and amiable,
并主张和平
and much inclined towards peace.
我发誓 举个例子
I swear, for example,
她会竭力阻止我与外国宣战
she would strive to prevent me taking part in a foreign war.
只是为避免与我分离的恐惧和痛苦
if only to avoid the fear and pain of separation.
如果发生战事 陛下 敌方是谁？
If you are on war, your majesty, against whom?
我只是打个比方
I was talking hypothetically.
当然 您自己会考虑这个问题的 大使阁下
Surely you'll do that youself, your excellency.
（英格兰北部 约克郡）
谢谢你们的到来 谢谢
Thanks for coming. Thank you.
朋友们 朋友们
Friends! Friends.
我们来到这里 是为了能够得到智者的指导
We've come here, so you can listen to and talk to.
罗伯特·阿斯克先生
this good man, Mr. Robert Aske.
你们有人知道他
Now some of you have already known him,
他是北安普顿公爵的律师
he is the Duke of Northampton's legal man.
他为人公正
He's always been honest and fair minded.
对平民百姓一视同仁
in these dealings with the commons so…
还是让阿斯克先生自己来讲吧
Mr. Aske can speak for himself.
女士们 先生们
Ladies and Gentlmen.
现在 说说你们是如何想的
Now, tell me what is your want.
阿斯克先生 我们的信仰的圣日都被废除 取消了
Mr Aske, all of our faith days were abolished and gone.
是否可以请求国王开恩恢复我们的圣日
Should it pleased the King's grace that we might have our Holy days back.
我们想修复我们的修道院
We want our abbeyes restored.
并要求停止推行异端邪说
And demand that this advance of heresy be halted.
我们希望这个新的邪恶主教克朗默被革除
We want this new heretic Bishop like Cranmer be casted off.
甚至克伦威尔也应该由出身高贵的人所替代
Even Cromwell to be surplanted by man of noble birth.
我们听说 阿斯克先生 要实行新的税收
We hear rumors, Mr. Aske, that new taxes levy's against us.
牲畜要征税 洗礼要征税
on our cattle, and our christenings,
甚至连结婚 生育都要征税
on our marriages, and our births.
阿斯克先生 他们甚至摧毁我们的教堂 窃取我们的财富
Aske, they even destroy our perish churches and steal our treasures.
我知道了 先生们 我知道了 先生们
All right, gentlemen. All right, gentlemen.
你们觉得 阻止他们的方法何在？
what do you reckon you can do to stop them.
阿斯克先生 在我们的土地 我们果实
Mr. Aske, before our lands, our good to their houses.
被国王特使们掠走之前 我们要战斗
are taken from by the church commissioners.We'll fight.
誓死战斗 直到取得胜利 阿斯克先生
and we'll die, die after full ultimate, Mr. Aske.
我知道你们都很愤怒
I know you are angry.
破坏修道院是一种卑劣行径 也是一种犯罪
the destruction of the abbeys is a terrible and criminal thing.
因为修道院就是我们所有人理想的现实代表
since that represents by that very presence and exotic ideal to of all of us.
但是先生们 武装起义 反叛国王
But gentlemen, this call to arms, to rebellion against the king's grace.
这超出我的道德底线 我不能苟同
is something which are my conscience I cannot agree to.
因为国王是我们的支柱
Since the King is our body and soul.
攻击他就等同于攻击国家 亵渎上帝
Then an attack upon him is an attack upon the commonwealth and upon God himself.
听到了吗 同伴们？
Did you hear that, my mates?
这位绅士不在乎我们
The gentry doesn't care for us.
基督为穷人而死
Christ die for the poor.
这你忘了吗 阿斯克先生？
Do you remember that, Mr. Aske?
厄苏拉·米塞尔登女士 王后陛下
Lady Misseldon, Your Majesty.
- 米塞尔登女士 - 王后陛下
- Lady Misseldon - Your Majesty.
请忠于职守
Do your duties honournably and virtuesly.
并记住 你们的职责就是服务与服从
and remember, you are all bound to serve and obey.
洛克福特女士？
Lady Rochford?
王后陛下
Your Majesty.
这边来
Please.
是我要求召见你
I ask to see you.
我知道自从你丈夫被处决后 你的处境并不太好
I know that the things have not gone well for you since your husband was executed.
我早已被这个世界无情地抛弃
I have been utterly abandoned.
我感到自己因为乔治的所作所为而备受指责
I feel I was condemed because of what George did.
甚至克伦威尔先生都拒绝回复我的信件
Even Mr Cromwell has refused to answer my letters.
这一切不是你的错 乔治·波林自食其果
Nothing was your fault.George Bolyen was his own keeper.
我希望你能回到王宫
I want you to come back to court.
我有意任命你为首席侍从女官
and I'd like to appoint you my principal lady in waiting.
希望你能接受这个任命
I hope you'll accept this position.
- 谢谢你 王后陛下 - 好了 洛克福特夫人
- Thank you, Your Majesty. - Well then, lady Rochford?
一切都会好起来的
all is well again.
一切都会弥补
All is mended up.
（杭斯顿宫 赫特福德郡）
弗兰西斯·布赖恩爵士参见 我的女士
Sir Francis Bryan, my lady.
- 玛丽女士 - 大人
- Lady Mary - My lord.
我很高兴你能来看我
I'm very glad you've come to see me.
我致函给国王恭贺其婚礼
I've written a letter congratulating the King on his marriage.
并请求去做珍王后侍从
And begging leave to wait upon queen Jane.
或是可以取悦王后的事务
or do her grace such services would please her to command me.
我恐怕 玛丽女士
I'm afraid, Lady Mary.
我不是来这里说客套话的
I've not come here to discuss pleasentaries.
国王陛下敦促你签署这份文件
His Majesty urged you to sign this.
- 这是什么？- 一个条款清单
- What is it? - A list of articles.
尊国王为教会领袖
Recognising the King as Head of the Church,
指认你母亲的婚姻是非法而乱伦的
and your mother's marriage just incestuous and unlawful.
你还必须脱离罗马教廷
You must also renounce Rome and.
并公开承认自己是私生女
free acknowledged of your illegitamacy.
如你不签 恐怕克伦威尔大臣阁下难保你安全
If you not sign, I'm afraid Mr Secretary Cromwell can not guarantee your safety.
无论我多么爱我的父亲 大人
However much I love my father, your grace.
并且愿意做任何事情来取悦和满足他 但我依然不能
And would do anything to please and satisfy him, I still cannot.
为了一个古怪国王的宠爱 出卖自己的灵魂
risk my mortal soul for the favor of an unearthly King.
你真是个不孝女
You're an unfitlial daughter.
既然你不服从你的父亲
Since you're not submit to your father.
那么接下来他也许会以叛国罪来处置你
He may yet procceed against you for treason.
不 不 他不会
No, no he would not.
- 我不相信 - 听我说
- I cannot believe it. - Listen to me.
我来告诉你
I tell you.
如果你是我的女儿
if you're my daugher,
我会用你的脑袋撞墙
I would smash your head against the wall.
直到软得如同煮烂的苹果
until it is soft as a boiled apple.
明白了吗？
Do you understand?
玛丽女士
Lady Mary.
我与荷尔拜因先生一起讨论了怎样为你加冕
I've been discussing plans for your coronation with Mr Holbein.
你听说过威尼斯的中心吗？
Have you ever heard of the centre of Venice?
没有 陛下
No, Your Majesty.
这是一艘船 每年威尼斯总督都会乘坐它出海
It's a ship. in which the Doge travels out.
在海上欢庆婚姻延绵
into the Lagoon every year to renew its marriage while the sea.
非常神奇的盛况 会伴随着满是金 铜雕像
It's a magnificant thing. The dawn will gold and bronze, statues of,
海神像 海狮和其他神奇的海洋生物
Neptune, sea lions and other fantastic sea creatures…
我准备建造它
And I'm going to build it.
而你将乘船出去旅行
and you're going go travel in it,
从格林威治到被加冕的城市
from Greenwich to the city,
正式成为英格兰王后珍
where you'll be crowned, Queen Jane of England.
陛下 此刻心情难以言表
Your Majesty, I… I don't know what to say.
你无需多言
You don't have to say anything.
这将是史上最隆重的英格兰王后加冕礼
It will be the most fabulous coronation any English Queen has ever had,
这一点我向你保证
that I promise you.
陛下 请原谅
Your Majesty. Forgive me.
听闻陛下
But I've heard Your Majesty.
起诉玛丽女士
make some proceedings against the Lady Mary.
我真心请求你不要如此
With all my heart I beg you not to.
你失去理智了吗
Are you out of your senses?
别再谈论此类事务
Don't talk of such matters again.
珍
Jane,
我还另有结婚礼物送给你
I have another wedding gift for you.
希望你喜欢
I hope you like it.
谢陛下
Thank you Your Majesty.
我喜欢 他太漂亮了
Oh I love him, he's so pretty.
米塞尔登女士
Lady Misseldon.
弗兰西斯阁下
Sir Francis.
- 希望我没吓着你 - 没有
- I hope I didn't alarm you. - No sir.
您留言说想见我
You left me a note that you wanted to see me?
是的
Yes, I did.
何事
About what?
我想知道
I was wondering.
你是否愿意作我的情妇
if you'd like to become my mistress.
阁下 我已订婚了
Sir, I'm already engage to be married.
和谁？
To whom?
罗伯特·泰维斯托克爵士
Sir Robert Tavistock.
他能给你买的起这样的礼物吗
Can he afford to buy you gifts like this?
我认为他做不到
I didn't think so.
但如果贞操对你更为重要的话
But if it's more important to you.
那也悉听尊便
to keep your virgin then keep it for what it's worth.
而且我发誓永不再烦扰你
And I swear I wouldn't bother you.
不会令你良心难安
or your conscience ever again.
我还没有决定
I haven't decided yet.
我怎能否认罗马或我母亲的婚姻
How can I renounce Rome or my mother's marriage.
尤其在她遭受那么多痛苦之后
After all of my mother's sufferings.
我理解
I understand.
但我建议你大可签署这份文件
But may I suggest that you could sign the document.
之后另书言明脱离与所谓新教的关系
And then make what is called a protestation apart.
此为有证人在场之摒弃你表面服从的秘密誓言
That is secretly foresware your submission before witnesses.
这岂不是虚伪？
Is that not hypocrisy?
我肯定皇帝以及教皇
Surely the emperor's against my signing such a document.
都会反对我签署该文件
and the Holy Father.
玛丽女士
Lady Mary,
我以实相告
I must tell you in honesty that.
皇帝陛下无意再
that the emperor's no longer inclined to.
进一步干涉此事
interfere any further in this matter.
你毕竟不是他的臣民
After all, you are not his subject and.
况且他正在寻求与英格兰缔结新盟约
and since he is seeking a new alliance with the king,
他不会做出任何冒犯英王之举
he would in truth be most reluctant.
他确实无法勉为其难
to offend him in any way.
那我只能孤军奋战了？
Then, I'm on my own?
如果我不签呢
What if I do not sign it?
那国王极有可能会致你于死地
It is very possible that the king would put you to death.
好吧
Well.
- 你… 你不先读一下？- 不必
- Do you…do you not want to read it first? - No.
我只请求你祈祷上帝赦免我的所为
Only I ask if you can pray for absolution for what I've done.
只要我还在世
So long as I live,
我永远不会原谅自己的
I will never forgive myself.
（意大利 甘道夫堡 教皇夏宫）
波尔神父？
Father Pole?
是的 殿下
Yes Your Eminence.
我是冯·瓦尔德堡红衣主教
I'm Cardinal Von Waldburg.
你追随来到罗马多久了 波尔神父？
How long have you been as the servant adhere in Rome, Father Pole?
将近一年 殿下
Almost a year Your Eminence.
我在英王有意表明脱离
I left England when to became clear that.
罗马教廷时离开的英国
the king meant to break his obedience to see of Roman, our Holy Father.
那个妓女安妮·波林死了或许是天意
The death of whore Anne Boleyn is perhaps providential.
教皇陛下祈盼英王亨利
And His Holiness prays that King Henry would.
可以抓住和解的神圣契机
grasp this divine opportunity for reconciliation.
哪怕仅仅一个姿态
Just one gesture,
倾向于罗马教廷 即使一个很微小的举动
of he sounds to see of Rome, however small,
就可使他免于被逐出教会之祸
will allow him to leave the threat of excommunication.
殿下请相信我
Your Eminence believe me,
那也是英国信徒所祈祷
that is something that the faithful of England are praying for.
我母亲 索尔兹伯里夫人在信中
My mother, Lady Salisbury has written to me.
表达了她的期望
expressing her hope that the new queen is.
新皇后是一位忠诚的天主教徒
in her heart a true Catholic.
除期待之外 令堂或许还可有所作为
Perhaps your mother could do more than hope.
或许波尔神父您
And perhaps you yourself Father Pole.
会考虑重返英格兰
might've considering returning to England.
以便影响事态发展
In order to influence events there.
你知道 波尔神父
You see, Father Pole,
我非常了解你
I know who you really are.
简直是达娜公主再世
here is the real Danae?
她会激发你的欲望高涨
She would kindle your lust even higher.
只需轻触她的玉体
One touch, one mere touch of her body,
就使你涌起烈焰般欲望 （引自《萨蒂利孔》）
and your limbs will melt in the fire.
项链很配你
The necklace suits you,
你可爱之极
and you're adored.
（约克郡）
奉圣父 圣子 及圣神之名 阿门
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti. Amen.
万福玛利亚 满被圣宠者 主与尔偕焉
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus tecum.
陛下 布赖恩女士
Your Majesty has received a letter from Lady Bryan,
伊丽莎白女士之监护人来信
governors to the Lady Elizabeth.
显然这孩子已长大 穿不下旧衣服了
Apparently the child has outgrown her clothes.
她要求陛下恩准
Lady Bryan asks if Your Majesty would permit.
为那孩子添置新衣
her to purchase new ones.
我非得如此吗 我都不相信她是我的骨肉
Why should I? I don't believe she is my child.
全世界都知道她父亲是亨利·诺里斯这个叛党
The whole world knows their father's a traitor Henry Norris.
她母亲就是个娼妇
and their mother was a whore.
还有何事
What else?
玛丽女士呈上了顺从函
There's letters, the submission of the Lady Mary.
你来安排
You will make arrangements.
我会亲自偕同王后面见她
for myself and the Queen to meet with her.
但不是在这 私下进行
Not here and not publicly.
我们可以去她的住处
We will go to her residence.
城内有关瘟疫的流言四起
There're rumors of plague in the city.
加冕礼无疑是要推迟了
Coronation would have to be postponed.
陛下
Your Majesty.
托马斯
Thomas.
理查德先生给我汇报了收入金额
Mr.Richard showed me the figures.
我对你甚为满意
I'm very pleased with you Tom.
我会很快施恩与你为证
I will shortly prove it.
洛克福特女士
Lady Rochford.
是 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
将这交予布赖恩女士
Take this to Lady Bryan,
令她为伊丽莎白女士添置衣物
tell her to use it buy clothes for the Lady Elisabeth.
是 夫人
Yes, Madam.
你还得考虑下玛丽女士的礼物
And you must think of a gift for the Lady Mary.
我热切期望能与她相见
I'm looking so forward to meeting her.
陛下宅心仁厚
Your Majesty is very kind.
洛克福特女士
Lady Rochford,
你丈夫背叛并非你的过错
it's not your fault that your husband betrayed you.
生于帝王之家
Nor is it Mary's fault or Elizabeth's fault.
也并非玛丽或伊丽莎白之错
to be born of a king.
女人多半是牺牲品
Women are much put upon in this world.
我恳切希望在我力所能及之内为她们争取利益
It's my desire as much as I can to promote their interests.
我会悄然行事
I must do it quietly.
但我会一如既往
But I will do it all the same.
我相信你能帮助我
And I trust you'd help me.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
姓名
What's your name, man?
查理 先生 查理·罗尔
Charlie, sir. Charlie Roll.
- 职业？- 牧羊人
- Trade? - Shepherd.
克伦威尔国务秘书阁下
Mr. Secretary Cromwell.
跪礼
Kneel.
查理 你是否已经了解清楚
Do you know well about it, Charlie?
是的 阿斯克首领
Yes, Captain Aske.
我等并非叛乱者
We're not rebels,
实为朝圣者
we're Pilgrimages.
我们将举行朝圣行动
And we have a pilgrimage to go on.
如果你想加入我们
If you want to join us.
那么请务必向我们万能的上帝
then you shall swear to be true to our mighty God.
向基督天主教会
To Christ Catholic Church.
向我们至高无上的国王
To our sovereign lord, the king.
向王国之内的平民百姓发誓 上帝保佑
And to the commons of this realm, so help you God.
我发誓
I do swear.
戴上徽章
Wear this badge.
上面印有基督之五伤
It show the five wounds of Christ.
证明平民们乃为基督而奋争
To prove that the commons will fight in Christ cause.
遵命 首领
Yes, captain.
- 上帝保佑你 查理 - 大人
- God bless you, Charlie. - Sir.
钦此 托马斯·克伦威尔阁下
Arise, Sir Thomas Cromwell,
亦即温布尔登的克伦威尔男爵
also Baron Cromwell of Wimbledon.
从即日起
And from this day forth,
就任掌玺大臣
Lord Privy Seal.
陛下
Majesty.
大人 大人
Your Grace. Your Grace.
可以吗 小伙子
May I, son?
上帝与你同在
God be with you Lad.
陛下真是慷慨
Your Majesty is too kind.
玛丽 物质礼物无可比拟内心的收获
Mary, gifts like these are easy compared with gifts of a heart.
能见到你们父女和解
It gives more pleasure than I can say.
对我来说幸莫大焉
to see you reconcile with your father.
- 玛丽 - 陛下
- Mary. - Your Majesty.
这是一千克朗
Here is enough for a thousand crowns.
但有所需 尽管开口
If you need anything else you need only ask.
谢陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
父亲
Father.
是 父亲
Yes, father.
玛丽那么恬美感性
Mary's so sweet and affectional.
堪称完美
She's everything I heard should be.
她于身具有的美德与善良
It seems to be no wonder she's so marvelous and beloved.
广为民众深深爱戴就不足为奇
for her virtue and goodness in the hearts of the people.
陛下当邀请她进宫 昭告天下
Your Majesty must invite her to the court, show her off.
陛下？
Your Majesty?
您为何都不和我说话
Why were you not speak to me?
因为我很失望
Because I'm disappointed.
为何
Why?
我为你还没有身孕而感到失望
I'm disappointed because you're not yet with child.
大人 大人
Lord, my lord, my lord.
我们有急情禀告
We have come here in great haste.
北部大部分地区
To tell you that the great part of the north.
以及林肯郡部分地区
as well as part of Lincolnshire.
突发反王叛乱
have risen in sudden rebellion against His Majesty.
平民叛乱者到处都是
There are master of commons everywhere.
叛乱者们四处燃起硝烟
The beacons of rebellion burning their own light to cross the hills.
四天之前
Just four days ago,
当我们在收税时
while we're collecting taxes and hectinsome.
我们被一帮愤怒的暴徒所埋伏
We were set upon by an angry mob.
他们掳走了其中一名名叫尼古拉·拜楼的特使
They captured one of the Commissioners call Nicolas Bello.
将他拖下马
Pull him down from his hourse.
鞭打折磨他致死
and beat him to death with their stave.
在这些人中 我们看到牧师也武装起来
Among them, my lord, we saw armed priests.
这些叛乱者叫嚣着他们的名字
Urging on these rebellion's names.
杀了他们 杀了他们
and cries "kill them, kill them".
我们还听说另外一人 威廉姆·里奇
Then we heard another man, william Lichie.
一个效忠于您托马斯·克伦威尔的人
who is known to be your servant Mr.Cromwell.
被吊死在树上
have been hanged from a tree.
这些叛乱分子想要求什么呢？
and what these Rebels said they want.
据目前所知 他们想保留他们的圣日
so far I can tell you, they want to keep their holy days.
他们要求恢复修道院 净化教会 而且
they want monasteries restored and their church unelested, and…
不再加税
no more taxed.
我听说他们已经宣布继续进军
I heard they declared they prospaid with their journey.
他们想要杀您 克伦威尔大人
They intend to kill you, my Lord Crownwell.
4至5个主教 还有里奇大法官
4 or 5 bishops, and Chancellor Richie.
罪名是掠夺教会财物 颠覆教会
as deviced taken church goods, and tearing down churches.
为什么当地士绅不去镇压这些反叛而只是坐等
why dont the local Gentry intervince and serpress these traitors and wait.
他们本该保护他们的土地甚于圣日
surely they want to protect their lands than Holy Days.
他们尝试过 但更多的叛乱者继续杀回来
they tried, but the Rebels then come back even greater.
有人说 克伦威尔大人 他们不止几百人
some say, my lord Crownwell, they are not hundreds.
而是数千信仰反叛者反对国王的教会改革
but thousands religion rebelions against the King's Church reforms.
你为何毫无察觉 你本该洞悉所发生的一切
why did you know, you are suposed to know everything that goes on here.
你禀告我只是略有反抗 而事实却相反
you told me there was little opposition, on the contrary.
你告诉我多数人欣然看到解散那些寺院
You told me that most people was glad to see such places dissolved.
你大错特错了
you were wrong.
你一无所知 混账
you didnot know anything, knave.
坐下 这么写
sit down, write this.
对我臣民无端起事
we take it as greatest unkindness, that our common.
我们认为此为最大恶意
unfearist objects should rise agasint without any grounds.
吾本无意夺取教会物资
As for taking the goods from perish Church which is never intended.
现却属意
yet even it had been intended… True subjects.
真我子民断不该对其王公以武力相向
would have not dealt with me, Their Princess in such Violence.
而本当谐从王意
but would petition me for that purpose.
今我命尔等叛乱者立刻返回家园 三缄其口
now I command you Rebels to go home, and say no more.
牢记尔等本分 你们生而本当听命于我 你们的国王
and remember your allegiance, you are duly bound to to obey me, your King.
此乃上帝诫令及天地自然法则
both by God's Commoments, and by the law of nature.
（林肯郡）
全体人民 集合了
All commands, stick together.
现在该揭竿而起了 从今往后
now it's the time to arise, for else ever.
前进 向约克郡进发
so forwards, forwrds to York.
不怕牺牲
Forwards in pain of death.
以上帝的名义 前进
Forwards in God's Name, Forwards.
在给约克郡的士绅们写信
Writing to the Gentry of Yorkshire.
提醒他们镇压叛乱的职责 否则罪责难逃
reminding them of their duties to suppress these traitors, penalties in not doing so.
是否可以考虑暂停教会特使的工作 等叛乱…
so any case, for suspending the work of church commisioners, until rebels …
绝不 借北方暴民之手
no, the only way to beat the king's.
打击国王权威的唯一办法
authority into the hands of rude people of North.
就是向他们表明王意继续宗教改革
is to show them King's intend to continue with reformation.
或者叫宗教改良 不管他们怎么说
and correction religion whatever they say.
不管他们怎么做
what ever they do.
什么事
yes.
大人
my lord.
叛乱分子已经夺取了林肯郡
the Rebels have taken Lincoln.
叛军的旗子在城门飘扬
the Rebels flag flies over city gate.
更多的叛军已向约克郡挺进
and more of them are now marching on York.
上帝啊
My God, Help us.
在我5岁时 我和母亲被送到伦敦 进入伦敦塔内
When I was 5, my mother and I were taken accross London, into the tower.
那时发生了针对我父王的叛乱
there was a rebelion against my father.
那些康沃尔叛军已经攻到了城墙
The Cornish rebels reached the city walls,
城内充满恐慌和畏惧
and inside everything was panic, fear.
既无消息来源 也无我父王军队
with no news at all, nor army of my father.
我母亲力图保持镇静 但其实吓坏了
my mother tried to remain calm, she was terrified.
我当时也是
So was I,
我那时以为所有人会被杀掉
I was sure we were both going to be killed.
我现命你为王室军队总指挥
I'm appointing you command of the Royal forces,
尽快赶到北方去
you will arrive North as soon as possible.
你会找到军火 不可久留
you will find guns and ordnances of hunger, but don't tarry there.
不会 陛下 我将悉遵王命 及更甚
No, Your Majesty, I will do all Your Majesty Commands and more.
这些暴民就是叛国者 查尔斯
these rebels are our traitors, Charles.
他们满是邪恶与罪孽
full of wretched and devilish intense.
必须严惩他们
they must be punished,
他们居然对他们的主公犯下大逆不道的反叛罪行
for their detestable and unmature sin of rebellion against their Sirvior.
就像我的父王 惩戒那些康沃尔郡人一样
just as my father, punish the cornishmen.
查尔斯 怎么回事
Charles, What is going on.
- 退下 - 遵命 公爵大人
- Leave us. - Yes Your Grace.
陛下已命我领军去北方平叛
His Majesty has charged me would lead his army against North Rebels.
你不必担心 我还有后援军队去包抄他们
You are not to worry, I will have my back enough men and arms to subdue them.
这很容易 国王已经承诺
easily, I have his Majesty's promise.
看在上帝的份上 希望他能遵守
I hope to God, He keeps it.
我很高兴接受此项任命
I'm happy to accept this charge.
克伦威尔才是一切的祸根
Crownwell is being blamed for everything,
叛军如有天助 意欲要取他的人头
and the Rebels is demanding his head with God's help.
我或许乐意奉上
I may will be able to deliver it.
掌玺大臣觐见
The Lord Privy Seal.
我将派遣沙福克公爵率领王室军队
I'll despatch Duke of Surffolk to the Royal Army.
你看我们是否该继续派遣第二支平叛军队
If we need to send the second army to destroy the rebels.
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Mejesty.
除非他们自行解散
unless they disperse.
责令沙福克公爵
and said 100 of their ringleaders to the Duke of Surffolk.
吊死百名叛军头目
of with halters around their necks.
并宣布我准许烧毁他们的所有财产
then he has our permission to burn to destroy all their goods.
以对我的臣民们以儆效尤
and make a fearful example of them to all of our subjects.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Majesty.
如果他们还不投降 克伦威尔先生
If still they do not submit, Mr. Cromwell,
我保证会全然毁灭他们
then I promise the utter destruction of them.
包括他们的妻子 子女
their wives and their children.
你明白吗 我将毁灭他们的一切
Do you understand me? I will destroy them all.
然后我就会把你毁掉 克伦威尔
and then I'll destroy you, Cromwell.